George P. Kontoudis

3242 Kim Engineering Building, College Park, MD 20742, USA

★ www.georgekontoudis.com ⋈ kont@umd.edu © (+1) 540 449-7026 ♦ Updated: June 21, 2023

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My primary research interests lie in the integration of **robotics**, **control theory**, and **machine learning**. What interests me most is the formulation of hybrid theoretical schemes and the development of novel robotic devices to bridge the gap between machine learning and autonomous systems. I am particularly interested in how learning algorithms and control theory can enable multi-agent systems to efficiently collaborate with minimal information exchange for robotic navigation and exploration tasks. Also, I contribute to the OpenBionics initiative on the design and development of robot hands and prosthetic devices.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Associate, University of Maryland Motion and Teaming Lab (PI: Michael Otte)	Jan 2022–present
Graduate Research Assistant, Virginia Tech Center for Marine Autonomy & Robotics (PI: Daniel J. Stilwell) Computational Multiphysics Systems Laboratory (PI: Tomonari Furukawa)	Aug 2018–Dec 2021 Aug 2016–Jul 2018
Undergraduate Research Assistant, National Technical University of Athens Control Systems Laboratory (PI: Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos)	Apr 2014–Mar 2016
Founder & Research Associate, OpenBionics	Sep 2014–present
EDUCATION	
PhD in Electrical Engineering, Virginia Tech Advisor: Daniel J. Stilwell Dissertation Title: "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration GPA: 3.94/4.00	2018–2021
MSc in Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech Advisors: Tomonari Furukawa & Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis Thesis Title: "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation" GPA: 4.00/4.00	2016–2018
Diploma (BSc & MSc) in Mechanical Engineering, National Technical University of Athens Advisor: Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos Thesis Title: "Design and Development of an Underactuated, Anthropomorphic Robot Hand"	2012–2016
BSc in Mechanical Engineering, University of West Attica	2005–2010
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	
Instructor, ENAE488O/788O Introduction to Autonomous Multi-Robot Swarms Department of Aerospace Engineering, University of Maryland	Spring 2023
Graduate Teaching Assistant, ME4005 Mechancal Engineering Lab I Department of Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech	Spring 2017
Graduate Teaching Assistant, ME4006 Mechancal Engineering Lab II Department of Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech	Fall 2016
AWARDS & HONORS	
2022 RSS Pioneer (Acceptance Rate: 35%) 2022 MRC Postdoctoral Fellowship (\$60K) 5 × IEEE Student Travel Support for IROS, ACC, and CDC 2 × Virginia Tech GSA Travel Fund Award for Humanoids and ICORR	2022 2022 2015, 2019–2021 2019, 2020

NSF Student Travel Grant for WuWNet (\$1K)	2019	
NTUA Thomaideion Award for IROS	2016	
Hackaday Prize, 2 nd place among 900 projects (\$10K)	2015	
Robotdalen Innovation Award, 1st place (SEK 100K)	2015	

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Mechanical Engineer, Sychem S.A.	Oct 2010-Aug 2015
Aircraft Maintenance Engineer Trainee, Olympic Aviation	May 2008–Jan 2010

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Manuscripts Under Review (J:UR)

- [4] George P. Kontoudis, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Fully Decentralized, Scalable Gaussian Process Training for Multi-Agent Learning."
- [3] George P. Kontoudis, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Fully Decentralized, Scalable Gaussian Process Prediction for Multi-Agent Learning."
- [2] Alkesh K. Srivastava, **George P. Kontoudis**, Michael Otte, "Bayesian Network Approach for Information Gathering using Path-Based Sensors."
- [1] Zirui Xu, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Online and Robust Intermittent Motion Planning in Dynamic and Changing Environments," *IEEE Transactions on on Neural Networks and Learning Systems.* (resubmitted)

Referred Journal Publications (J)

- [4] **George P. Kontoudis**, Stephen Krauss, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Model-Based Learning of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance for Marine Robots," *Robotics and Autonomous Systems*, 2021.
- [3] Geng Gao, Mojtaba Shahmohammadi, Lucas Gerez, **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, "On Differential Mechanisms for Underactuated, Lightweight, Adaptive Prosthetic Hands," *Frontiers in Neurorobotics*, 2021.
- [2] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Kinodynamic Motion Planning with Continuous-Time Q-Learning: An Online, Model-Free, and Safe Navigation Framework," *IEEE Trans. on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*, 2019.
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, Tomonari Furukawa, "An Adaptive Actuation Mechanism for Anthropomorphic Robot Hands," *Frontiers in Robotics and AI*, 2019.

Chapters in Edited Volumes (BC)

[1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, Zirui Xu, "RRT-QX: Real-Time Kinodynamic Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments with Continuous-Time Reinforcement Learning," in *Brain and Cognitive Intelligence: Control in Robotics*, B. Wei (Ed.), Taylor & Francis Group, CRC Press, 2022.

Referred Conference Publications (C)

- [16] **George P. Kontoudis**, Michael Otte, "Exploration-Exploitation Active Learning of Gaussian Process Surrogates for Adaptive Sampling," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Detroit, USA, 2023.
- [15] **George P. Kontoudis**, Michael Otte, "Closed-Form Active Learning of Expected Variance Reduction using Gaussian Process Surrogates for Adaptive Sampling," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, San Diego, USA, 2023.
- [14] Alkesh K. Srivastava, **George P. Kontoudis**, Donald Sofge, Michael Otte, "Distributed Multi-Robot Information Gathering using Path-Based Sensors in Entropy-Weighted Voronoi Regions," *International Symposium on Distributed Autonomous Robotic Systems (DARS)*, Montbéliard, France, 2022.
- [13] Christos N. Mavridis, **George P. Kontoudis**, John S. Baras, "Sparse Gaussian Process Regression using Progressively Growing Learning Representations," *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)*, Cancun, Mexico, 2022.
- [12] Josh Netter, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Bounded Rational RRT-QX: Multi-Agent Motion Planning in Dynamic Human-Like Environments Using Cognitive Hierarchy and Q-Learning," *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)*, Austin, USA, 2021.

- [11] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Decentralized Nested Gaussian Processes for Multi-Robot Systems," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021.
- [10] Minas Liarokapis, **George P. Kontoudis**, "Teaching Robotic and Biomechatronic Concepts with a Gripper Design Project and a Grasping and Manipulation Competition," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021.
- [9] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Prediction of Acoustic Communication Performance in Marine Robots Using Model-Based Kriging," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, New Orleans, USA, 2021.
- [8] Gal Gorjup, **George P. Kontoudis**, Anany Dwivedi, Geng Gao, Saori Matsunaga, Toshisada Mariyama, Bruce MacDonald, and Minas Liarokapis "Combining Programming by Demonstration with Path Optimization and Local Replanning to Facilitate the Execution of Assembly Tasks," *IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man and Cybernetics (SMC)*, Toronto, Canada, 2020.
- [7] **George P. Kontoudis**, Zirui Xu, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Online, Model-Free Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments: An Intermittent, Finite Horizon Approach with Continuous-Time Q-Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Denver, USA, 2020.
- [6] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "A Comparison of Kriging and Cokriging for Estimation of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance," *ACM Int. Conf. on Underwater Networks and Systems (WuWNet)*, Atlanta, USA, 2019.
- [5] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019.
- [4] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "A Compliant, Underactuated Finger for Anthropomorphic Hands," *IEEE/RAS-EMBS Inter. Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019.
- [3] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Robust Kinodynamic Motion Planning using Model-Free Game-Theoretic Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, USA, 2019.
- [2] Kyriakos D. Tsoukalas, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Active-Bayesian Learning for Cooperation Connectivity in Dynamic Cyber-Physical-Human Systems," *IEEE Symposium on Adaptive Dynamic Programming and Reinforcement Learning (ADPRL)*, Honolulu, USA, 2017.
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "Open-Source, Anthropomorphic, Underactuated Robot Hands with a Selectively Lockable Differential Mechanism: Towards Affordable Prostheses," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Hamburg, Germany, 2015.

Preprints (P)

[1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Fully Decentralized, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Multi-Agent Federated Learning," *arXiv preprint*, *arXiv*:2203.02865, 2022.

Referred Workshop Publications (W)

- [2] Alkesh K. Srivastava, George P. Kontoudis, Donald Sofge, Michael Otte, "Path-Based Sensors: Will the Knowledge of Correlation in Random Variables Accelerate Information Gathering?" *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), Workshop on Communication Challenges in Multi-Robot Systems: Perception, Coordination, and Learning*, London, UK, June 2023.
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Scalable Multi-Robot Active Exploration," *Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS), Pioneers Work-shop*, New York City, USA, June 2022.

Theses (T)

- [3] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration," *Doctoral Dissertation, Virginia Tech*, USA, December 2021.
- [2] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation," *Master Thesis, Virginia Tech*, USA, December 2018.
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Design and Development of an Underactuated, Anthropomorphic Robot Hand," *Diploma Thesis*, *National Technical University of Athens*, March 2016. (in Greek)

Technical Reports (TR)

- [2] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "How to Create Affordable, Anthropomorphic, Light-Weight Prosthetic Hands," *Control Systems Lab, National Technical University of Athens*, Athens, Greece, October 2015.
- [1] Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Minas Liarokapis, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "How to Create Affordable, Modular, Light-Weight, Underactuated, Compliant Robot Hand," *Control Systems Lab, National Technical University of Athens*, Athens, Greece, January 2015.

TALKS & PRESENTATIONS

- · "Closed-Form Active Learning Using Expected Variance Reduction of Gaussian Process Surrogates for Adaptive Sampling" American Control Conference (ACC), San Diego, USA, 2023. [Oral Presentation]
- · "Decentralized Gaussian Process Learning for Exploration with Multi-Robot Systems" *Maryland Robotics Center Research Symposium*, College Park, USA, May 2023. [Oral Presentation Invited Talk]
- · "Scalable Exploration-Exploitation Active Learning of Gaussian Process Surrogates for Adaptive Sampling" *Maryland Robotics Center Research Symposium*, College Park, USA, May 2023. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Multi-Robot Adaptive Sampling using Decentralized Gaussian Processes," *International Symposium on Distributed Autonomous Robotic Systems (DARS)*, Monbeliard, France, November 2022. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Scalable Multi-Robot Active Exploration," *Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS)*, *Pioneers Workshop*, New York City, USA, June 2022. [Spotlight Presentation]
- · "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration" *Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Virginia Tech*, Blacksburg, USA, December 2021. [PhD Defense]
- · "Decentralized Nested Gaussian Processes for Multi-Robot Systems," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021. [Virtual Presentation]
- · "Online, Model-Free Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments: An Intermittent, Finite Horizon Approach with Continuous-Time Q-Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Denver, USA, 2020. [Rapid-Interactive Presentation]
- · "A Comparison of Kriging and Cokriging for Estimation of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance," *ACM International Conference on Underwater Networks and Systems (WuWNet)*, Atlanta, USA, 2019. [Oral Presentation]
- · "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," Workshop on New Challenges in Humanoid Grasping and Manipulation in IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids), Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Oral Presentation Invited Talk]
- · "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Robust Kinodynamic Motion Planning using Model-Free Game-Theoretic Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, USA, 2019. [Oral Presentation]
- · "A Compliant, Underactuated Finger for Anthropomorphic Hands," *IEEE/RAS-EMBS International Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation," *Department of Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech*, Blacksburg, USA, December 2018. [Master's Defense]
- · "Evaluation Strategies of Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Dexterous In-Hand Manipulation: Early Results," *National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)*, USA, 2018. [Invited Talk]
- · "Open-Source, Anthropomorphic, Underactuated Robot Hands with a Selectively Lockable Differential Mechanism: Towards Affordable Prostheses," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Hamburg, Germany, 2015. [Oral Presentation]

SERVICE ACTIVITIES

Conference Committees	
· General Chair, Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS), Pioneers Workshop	2023
· Program Committee Member, Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), Student Abstract and Poster	2023
· Online Platform Chair, Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL)	2022

D	Tarres ala	
Reviewer,	Journais	j

Reviewer, Journals	
· IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems	2019–2022
· IEEE Transactions on Robotics	2020, 2023
· IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering	2020–2023
· IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics	2020
IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man and Cybernetics: Systems	2021
IEEE Computational Intelligence Magazine	2020
IEEE Control Systems Letters	2019, 2020
IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters	2019, 2022, 2023
IEEE Robotics & Automation Magazine	2022
Autonomous Robots	2022
Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence	2021
Frontiers in Robotics and AI	2022
Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications	2021
International Journal of Advanced Robotic Systems	2015, 2016
Reviewer, Conferences	
IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)	2018–2023
IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)	2018–2023
American Control Conference (ACC)	2018–2021
IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)	2019, 2020, 2023
IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE)	2019
IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)	2019
IEEE International Conference on Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics (BioRob)	2018, 2020, 2021
European Control Conference (ECC)	2022
Mediterranean Conference on Control and Automation (MED)	2018
ENTORING	
PhD Students	
Joshua Netter, Georgia Institute of Technology	2021–present
Advisor: Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis	
Master's Students	
Alkesh K. Srivastava, University of Maryland	2022–present
Advisor: Michael Otte	
Publications: C-[14], W-[2], J:UR-[2]	
Joshua Netter, Georgia Institute of Technology	2020–2021
Advisor: Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis	
Publications: C-[12]	2010 2020
Zirui Xu, Georgia Institute of Technology,	2018–2020
Advisor: Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis	
Publications: C-[7], BC-[1], J:UR-[1] Currently: PhD Candidate, University of Michigan	
Currently. Find Candidate, Oniversity of Wilcingan	